Marilyn Nelson Papers
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Marilyn Nelson Papers.
1963-2001.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center
Nelson, Marilyn.
2 linear feet.
The collection contains the papers of Marilyn Nelson, author of several books of poetry and current Poet Laureate for the State of Connecticut.
MSS19920056
Biography
Marilyn Nelson was born 26 April 1946 to Johnnie E. Nelson and Melvin Nelson, Sr. She is a graduate of Hiram Johnson High School and the University of California at Davis, and has a Master's degree from the University of Pennsylvania. She is the author of 6 books of poetry, 2 children's collections and a few chapter books. Her book Carver: A life in Poems has been awarded the Boston Globe-Horn Book Award for excellence in children's literature. The Homeplace was a finalist for the National Book Award and the Lenore Marshall Prize and won the 1998 Poet's Prize. Nelson has received a Guggenheim Fellowship and recently named Connecticut's Poet Laureate by the Connecticut Commission on the Arts. Marilyn Nelson has been teaching at the University of Connecticut since 1978.
Nelson Bibliography
[As Marilyn Nelson Waniek]. For the Body, Louisiana State University Press, 1978.
[As Marilyn Nelson Waniek]. The Cat Walked through the Casserole and Other Poems for Children, Carolrhoda, 1984.
[As Marilyn Nelson Waniek]. Mama's Promises, Louisiana State University Press, 1985.
[As Marilyn Nelson Waniek]. The Homeplace, Louisiana State University Press, 1990.
[As Marilyn Nelson Waniek]. Magnificat, Louisiana State University Press, 1994.
[Translator] Pil Dahlerup. Literary Sex Roles, Minnesota Women in Higher Education, 1975.
[Translator with Espeland] Halfdan Rasmussen. Hundreds of Hens and Other Poems for Children, Black Willow Press, 1982.
Carver: A Life in Poems, Front Street, 2001.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence from Nelson's MFA students at Vermont College and from other poets, personal notebooks, photographs, manuscripts of poetry and translations and term papers written while Nelson was a student.
Organization
Series I: Poetry Correspondence and Manuscripts (undated, 1964- 1992) contains term papers while Nelson was a student, manuscripts of poetry, poems written with childern, correspondence from theologian Mary Pellauer; poets Dave Smith and others, and translation of Thornvig Bjorvig poems.
Series II: Other Correspondence and Photographs (1986-1992) from MFA students at Vermont College and magazines as well as photographs.
Related Material
Archives and Special Collections have a substantial collection of literary manuscripts and faculty papers. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection has been reordered and divided into two series. Photographs were removed from original folders and placed in a separate folder created for photographs. Publications were also removed for cataloging.
Separated Material
Motley, Volume 2, Number 1, Winter 1964. Dodd Periodicals
Moving Out: Feminist Literary & Arts Journal, Volume 5, Number 1, 1975. Dodd Periodicals
Christianity and Crisis, Volume 44, No 13, August 13, 1984. Dodd Periodicals
Touchstone: Viterbo College, Vol. 25, 26, Spring 1974, 1975. Dodd Periodicals
The Pennsylvania Gazette, Vol. 69. No. 5, March, 1971. Dodd Periodicals
Bibliography
Dictionary of Literary Biography, Volume 120: American Poets since World War II, Third Series, Gale, 1992.
Booklist, September 1, 1994.
Hudson Review, Summer, 1991.
Kenyon Review, Spring, 1991.
Multicultural Review, March, 1995.
Parnassus, Volume 17, number 1, 1992.
Publishers Weekly,, November 16, 1990; August 29, 1994
School Library Journal, June, 1991.
Shenandoah, Winter, 1992.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Nelson, Marilyn.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut--Faculty.; Poets--United States.; Poets laureate--Connecticut.; American poetry--20th century.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Poems.
Occupations:
Poet.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions to materials identified in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Professor Marilyn Nelson donated her collection in 1992.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Poetry Correspondence and Manuscripts,undated, 1964-1992
  - Genealogy, undated (Box 1:1)
  - Letter to Jacob Nelson, undated (Box 1:2)
  - Term Papers, 1964-1965 (Box 1:3)
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 1:4)
  - Agte/ Anderson/ Ashbery/ Bursk/ Burkholder/ Camoin/ Da Costa/ Espenland, 1986,1989,1991 (Box 1:5)
  - Dean, Debra, 1987-1992 (Box 1:6)
  - Gibson/ Gifford/ Gompert/ Hoehandel/ Hoffman/ Hudgins/ Johnston, 1983-1986,1991 (Box 1:7)
  - Knight/ Komunyakaa/ Kelly/ Levine/ Louis/ Martin/ McDowell/ Myers, 1995-1988,1991-1992 (Box 1:8)
  - Nelson, Peter, 1976-1978, 1992 (Box 1:9)
  - Nicholas/ O`Brien/ Rivers/ Sevlly/ Smith, 1984-1987,1991-1992 (Box 1:10)
  - Pellauer, Mary, 1977, 1981-1992 (Box 1:11)
  - Solgiano, P., 1977-1986 (Box 1:12)
  - Thenior, Ralf, 1977-1987 (Box 1:13)
  - Vernon/ Whiting, 1979, 1990 (Box 1:14)
  - Wojahn, David, 1977-1985 (Box 1:15)
  - Thornkild, Bjornvig, 1984-1988 (Box 1:16)
  - Poems, 1966 (Box 1:17)
  - Poems, 1967-1968 (Box 1:18)
  - Poems, 1969 (Box 1:19)
  - Poems, 1970-1971 (Box 1:20)
  - Poems, 1972-1975 (Box 1:21)
  - Poems, 1976-1978 (Box 1:22)
  - Poems, 1983 (Box 1:23)
  - Poems, 1989 (Box 1:24)
  - Poems, 1990 (Box 1:25)
  - Poems, undated (Box 1:26-40)
  - Poems, undated (Box 2:41-47)
  - "Alphabet Bestiaries", 1984, 1986 (Box 2:48)
  - "The Perfect Principal" (Poems written with children), 1987 (Box 2:49)
  - "Selected Poems of Thornkild Bjornvig" (Translated by Marilyn Nelson), undated (Box 2:50)
- Series II: Other Correspondence and Photographs,1986-2001
  - Townsend, Alison, 1991 (Box 2:51)
  - Lister, Kay, 1991 (Box 2:52)
  - Davis, Robin Elizabeth, 1991 (Box 2:53)
  - 13 Moon: A Feminist Literary Magazine/ The Kenyon Review/ The Southern Review, 1986-1990, 1992 (Box 2:54)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2:55)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1992-1993, 2001 (Box 2:56)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 2:57)